The third point she made was that once you've taken refuge in the Three Jewels, you
Ý thứ ba cô nói là đã quy y Tam Bảo thì
shouldn't go to a fortune teller, but is it permissible to go to a fortune teller to choose an auspicious
không được đi xem bói nhưng có được đi
date and time for a family
xem ngày giờ khi gia đình mình có công
event?  That's like going to see a fortune teller.   Just
việc không? Như thế là đi xem bói rồi.
ask the monk, okay?  The
Hỏi thầy chùa mình là được nhá. Thầy
monk said, "My son has a wedding or
chùa là con bạch thầy nhà con có đám
engagement ceremony at home. So, I'll check
cưới đám hỏiế này thì con xem con đi đám
which day I should attend the wedding and which day I should attend the engagement ceremony. Do you all understand
cưới ngày nào hỏi ngày nào đại chúng rõ
this?"  But actually, there are no good
chỗ này chưa? Nhưng thực chất ra là chả
or bad days.
có ngày nào là ngày xấu ngày đẹp đâu.
This day was created by humans, it is outside the
Đây ngày là do con người đặt ra nó ngoài
law of cause and effect.  Do you understand this part?
nhân quả. Đ chúng rõ chỗ này chưa?
For now, Yen will only say this much.  It was only in
Bây giờ Yến chỉ nói thế này thôi. Riêng
1945 that Vietnam
cái năm 45 ấy của đất nước Việt Nam mình
suffered from famine, not the neighboring country
mới chết đói chứ chứ đất nước cạnh nó có
.  So, that year, Vietnam was the only
chết đói đâu. Thế cái năm đấy là riêng
country with a single
đất nước Việt Nam mình một mình một sao
unlucky day, like a star in the sky?  Are there no auspicious days according to the
một toàn ngày xấu à. Không có ngày hoàng
lunar calendar?  It was an auspicious day, but a bomb
đạo à? Ngày hoàng đạo mà một quả bom nó
dropped and killed everyone.
bỏ chết hết luôn.
Will the zodiac animal die if a bomb is dropped?   Even though
Bom bỏ ngài hoàng đạo có chết không?
he was thought to be invulnerable to bombs
Tưởng là ngài hoàng đạo bom bỏ không
, he
chết được,
still died as usual.  Then that's definitely
vẫn chết như thường. Thế thì chính tỏ là
karma.  Therefore, as Buddhists, we
nghiệp rồi nhá. Cho nên là Phật tử chúng
shouldn't pay attention to auspicious dates and times anymore.  Instead of focusing on
ta đừng có coi ngày giờ nữa. Không phải
work hours, use that time to teach
ngày giờ làm lên mà thời gian đó đi dạy
your children and grandchildren about the law of karma.
con cháu mình tu nhân quả đi. Còn nếu
If we teach our children and grandchildren about time and date,
như mình dạy con cháu mình ngày giờ thì
they will forget about the law of karma.  If it's attributed to the timing,
nó sẽ bỏ nhân quả. Nó đổ tại ngày giờ mà
then it will deviate from the law of cause and effect.  Is it
thì nó sẽ xa rời nhân quả. thả rằng dạy
right to teach your children to live with filial piety and integrity
con mình sống có hiếu, có nghĩa đúng
?  Being grateful, forgiving, and a good listener will bring
không? Biết ơn, biết tha thứ, biết lắng
blessings to your family.  It will increase
thì nhà mình có phúc nhá. Sẽ tăng thêm
blessings, but if we keep blaming it on the time and date,
phúc chứ còn cứ đổ tại ngày giờ thì con
people will forget about cultivating character
người ta sẽ quên đi mất rèn dũa tư cách
and completely disregard it.  Now, Yen
mà lỏ hoàn toàn là ngày giờ. Bây giờ Yến
asks, "If you keep checking the auspicious days and times,
hỏi nhá, bây giờ cứ đi xem ngày giờ ngày
and you go stealing on any day,
nào ngày hoàng đạo cũng đi ăn trộm
do you understand?"
có hiểu bát không?
If you can assure me that this
Nếu mà ông cam đoan với tôi ngày này của
is a beautiful day for me, an extremely beautiful day, a day so beautiful that
tôi là ngày đẹp, ngày cực đẹp,
I could commit robbery without any consequences, then it would be
tôi đi ăn cướp cũng không bị làm sao thì
considered a beautiful day.  But if those who do evil will
mới gọi là ngày đẹp. Chứ còn làm việc ác
still face retribution, then it proves there is no fixed
vẫn bị quả báo thì chính tỏ không có
day or time.  Right?
ngày giờ. Phải không?
Yen has told this story over and over again. When she
Cái chuyện này Yến kể đi kể lại kể nhiều
went to the engagement ceremony for
lần rồi Yến đi mới đi đám hỏi cho cái
this family back then, it was all the way in
nhà này hồi đấy là ở tận ngoài ngoài
Tien Yen, and it was 3 o'clock, I think 17 minutes later, before she was even
Tiên Yên 3 giờ hình như là 17 phút là
allowed to enter the door.
mới được bước vào cửa.
And when the Yen group goes there, they have to rent
Mà hội Yến đi ra đấy là phải thuê khách
this hotel to stay.
sạn này ở.
After finishing the offerings, you have to figure out how to
ở xong bày lễ xong phải căn như thế nào
line up and stand outside.  Because at
đấy mà xếp hàng đứng ở ngoài. Tại vì
exactly 3:17, the door must open, and the first person
đúng 3:17 mở cửa là phải người đầu tiên
to step through the door must be there.
bước vào qua cửa.
But it seems like we have to leave the house at 3:25 or 30 minutes
Mà hình như là 3:25 hay 30 phút là phải
.  Before they could even have a drink or a
ra khỏi cửa. Chưa kịp uống nước, chưa
conversation, they only mentioned
kịp hai bên nói chuyện mới có chỉ nói là
waiting until the engagement ceremony before getting up and leaving.   They
để đến lễ hỏi là đứng lên đi về.
broke up less than a year later.
Chưa được một năm hai đứa đã bỏ nhau.
Because people no longer teach their children
Bởi vì người ta không dạy con người ta
morality; everything is based entirely on the date and
đạo đức nữa mà hoàn toàn căn cứ vào ngày
time.  How can that transformation be achieved, my
giờ. Làm sao mà có thể chuyển hóa được
esteemed fellow practitioners?  Whenever her husband
phải không quý đạo hữu? Hơi một tí chồng
has a problem, she doesn't even consider the possibility
có việc gì thì lại không tính đến cái
of correcting his behavior.
chuyện là rèn sửa hành vi.
This cause and effect led to this action;
Nhân quả này mày ra hành vi này, nhân
this cause and effect led to this action—this cause and
quả này ra hành vi này phải chuyển nhân
effect must be shifted.  Transforming behavior into cause and
quả đi. Chuyển hành vi thế ra chuyển
effect.  At most, spiritual actions
nhân quả. cùng lắm là các hành vi về tâm
, combined with actions in the
linh nữa, kết hợp với hành vi trong hiện
present moment, will solve the problem.
tại thì nó sẽ giải quyết được vấn đề.
But simply setting a date and time won't
Thế nhưng mà cứ ngày giờ thôi thì có
solve anything.  As a result, they
giải quyết được đâu. Thành ra là chưa
broke up in less than a year, so
được một năm anh chị đã bỏ nhau mất rồi
how could they have gotten married twice?  They had an engagement ceremony,
còn đâu mà lại cưới hai lần. Ăn hỏi như
but then they got married twice.   They get
thế nhưng cưới lại còn cưới hai lần nữa.
married once, then have a fake wedding ceremony, and then
Một lần cưới rồi xong lại giả lễ xong
get married again to avoid
lại cưới tiếp một lần nữa để cho đỡ bỏ
separating.  Because when we went to have our fortunes told, the fortune teller
nhau. Vì đi xem số má gì ấ thì ông thầy
did it that way.  They still broke up,
ông làm cho như thế. Bỏ nhau vẫn hoàn bỏ
and our ancestors during the war of
nhau mà các cụ nhà ta thời chiến tranh
resistance didn't have any specific dates or times for such separations.
kháng chiến ấ làm gì có ngày giờ đâu. Cứ
Weddings happen every Saturday and Sunday.  Do you old
thứ bảy chủ nhật là đám cưới. Các cụ già
folks agree?  In the old days,
các cụ có thấy đúng không? Hồi xưa thứ
workers only got Saturdays and Sundays
bảy chủ nhật thì công nhân mới được
off.  That's why they always have weddings on
nghỉ. Cho nên là chuyên đám cưới vào thứ
Saturdays and Sundays, because if they don't have weddings on any other day or time, they'll inevitably break up
bảy chủ nhật chứ làm gì ngày giờ đâu mà
.  Are these people living ethically
chả bỏ nhau cả. Người ta sống có đạo đức
?  Okay then.  So, going to a
đúng không? Thế nhá. Cho nên là đi xem
fortune teller is considered superstition.  No fortune telling about auspicious
bói là mê tín rồi đấy. Không xem bói
days or times, okay?  It's best if
ngày giờ gì cả nhá. Tốt hơn hết là chúng
we check the weather forecast to see
ta cứ mở cái bảng thời tiết ra xem là
when the weather is suitable for
lúc nào mưa nắng phù hợp với công việc
our household chores, then we can proceed.  So, there are
nhà mình thì mình tiến hành. Đấy, còn
things we can't control, like whether it's the
những cái mà mình không làm chủ được tức
bride's side or the
là bên kia nhà mình là nhà gái, bên kia
groom's side, and we just have to accept it.
là nhà trai mình phải chịu thôi nhá. Chứ
I don't actively engage in superstitious practices
còn mình không chủ động làm các việc mê
.  When our family wants to get
tín. Mà khi nhà mình muốn cưới gả con
married, build a house, or do all sorts of other things,
cái, xây nhà, xây cửa tất cả các thứ
if our parents are still alive, we
mình nên là nếu có cha mẹ mình còn sống
should create something to take care of them
thì nên tạo ra cái gì mà chăm sóc cha mẹ
.   The
mình.
ancestors and obedient spirits will take
Tổ tiên và các vong linh ngoan ra chế
control, just like you esteemed fellow practitioners.  So,
chủ là xong như các quý đạo hữu nhá. Thế
write and do good deeds.
và viết làm các cái việc phước lành.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]